Guide to the David A. Kessler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David A. Kessler papers
1950-2000
MS 1796
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
71.25
(81 boxes)
The papers include speeches, office files, videotapes, and other materials that document Kessler's tenure as commissioner of the United States Food and Drug Administration, particularly his role in the campaign to regulate nicotine as a controlled substance. The collection also contains interviews of tobacco company executives, government officials, researchers, and other individuals that Kessler conducted in the course of writing his book A Question of Intent.
Kessler, David A., 1951-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Kessler, 2005-2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Video tapes in boxes 27-32 and audio tapes in boxes 52-68 and 71-72 may not be played; researchers must have use copies made.
Computer disks in Series VIII are closed until processed.
Arrangement
Arranged in nine series: I. General Files, 1953-2000; II. Speeches, 1990-2000; III. Chronological Files, 1977-1997; IV. Food and Drug Administration Commissioner's Files, 1952-1997; V. Scrapbooks, 1990-1991; VI. Briefing Books, 1950-1997; VII. Video Tapes, 1990-1997; VIII. Interviews, 1994-2000; IX. Informant Files, 1961-1998.
Scope and Contents
The David A. Kessler Papers are almost entirely comprised of materials documenting Kessler's tenure as commissioner of the Food and Drug Administration (1990-1997). There are no materials documenting his professional or personal life prior to his confirmation as FDA commissioner, and other than speeches, there is no documentation of his term as dean of the Yale University School of Medicine (1997-).
The majority of the Papers were assembled by Kessler as he researched and wrote A Question of Intent (2001, Public Affairs), a recounting of his tenure as FDA commissioner and a study of the attempt by the FDA to secure regulation of nicotine as a drug. In the course of the book preparation, the author created various filing systems for the documentation and there was overlap and duplication between systems. Kessler's filing system has been maintained in the organization of the papers and researchers will often need to search several series to ensure they have located all materials on a given subject. The documentation collected by Kessler from tobacco company websites, legal suits against the tobacco companies, and various governmental hearings about the addictive nature of nicotine were not accessioned. Of the remaining materials, emphasis was placed on capturing documentation and files that were created or generated specifically by Kessler.
Given the wide availability, particularly on the Internet, of once secret tobacco company documents and other materials related to the health consequences of smoking, and their permanent preservation by the Tobacco Control Archives of the University of California at San Francisco (www.library.ucsf.edu/tobacco/), the most significant research material in the Kessler papers are the transcripts of the many interviews he conducted for his book. The persons interviewed ranged from government officials, leaders of anti-smoking organizations, reporters for major newspapers, and partners in law firms, to employees of tobacco companies. Other issues of concern to Kessler as FDA commissioner included accurate labeling of the contents of food products, breast implants, drug tampering, and adequate funding for the agency. They are primarily documented in the General Files, FDA Files, and Briefing Books series.
Biographical / Historical
David A. Kessler was born May 31, 1951, in New York City. He graduated magna cum laude from Amherst College in 1973 and received a law degree from the University of Chicago in 1978, an M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1979, and an advanced certificate in business from New York University's Graduate School of Business Administration in 1986. Kessler served as special assistant to the president of Montefiore Medical Center (1982-1984) and as medical director of The Hospital of the Albert Einstein College of Medicine before being appointed as the commissioner of the United States Food and Drug Administration (1990-1997). From 1997 to 2003, Kessler was dean of the Yale University School of Medicine. In 2003, Kessler became the dean and vice chancellor of medical affairs at the University of California San Francisco School of Medicine.
Other Finding Aids
For an index of author interviews, please consult the Author Interviews Index.
Nicotine -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History; Smoking -- Law and legislation; Tobacco industry -- United States -- History; Tobacco -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History; Kessler, David A., 1951-; United States. Food and Drug Administration -- History; Philip Morris and Company; R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Company; Yale University -- Faculty
- General Files, 1953-2000, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, the series includes memoranda, correspondence, reports, and other documents related to a variety of public health issues, but predominantly tobacco. Folder titles and headings created by Kessler and his staff have been preserved. There is considerable overlap and possible duplication with Series III and Series IV.
  - Abusive mail, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Action on Smoking and Health, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, David, 1994,undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Addison/Yeamen documents, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adolescents [cigarette warnings], 1989-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Advertisements
    - Cigarettes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Smoking, 1962, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
    - Youth, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Advisory Committee on Tobacco Policy and Public Health [press conference], 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Airlie House meeting, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alcohol and caffeine, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Animal research guidelines, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Apology accepted advertisement in Day One story, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Autoimmune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)
    - Didanosine (ddI), 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Treatment Action Group (TAG), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Backgrounder" materials, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Baker, Senator, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ballin, Scott, 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Barrett, Stephen [dietary supplements], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Barry, Herbert III, 1986-1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barton, Joe, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22 - 29)
  - Battle behind the smoke screen, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Beavens action, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bender, Jonathan, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bergman, Lowell and New York Daily News, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Berlind, Mark H. re: Talk of the Nation, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bernstein, Ilisa, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 35 - 41)
  - Biotechnology companies with oncology products in the clinic, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Blilely, Thomas J. [letters to FDA after March and June hearings], 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Blood testing, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - "Blue Darters" early briefings, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bogdanich, Walt, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Book proposal [Kessler], 1997 (Box 1, Folder 47 - 48)
  - Breast implants, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - British
    - Development on tobacco, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Killing statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Brown and Williamson [mostly regarding May 3, 1994 visit], 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 52 - 57)
  - Brown, Peter H. re: Victor DeNoble autobiography, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Budich, Kevin [mostly notes], 1991-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 59 - 65)
  - Burros, Marian - Chinese restaurant, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Burzynski, Stanislav, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 67 - 68)
  - Caffeine, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Calendar [Jerry Mande important dates], undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Campbell, William I., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Canadian tobacco control, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Cancer, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Carter/Califano, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - "Case Against the Little White Slaver", undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Center for Applied Research [campaign approach to strategic change], 1999 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Centers for Disease Control, 1992, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 78 - 79)
  - Centocor, 1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - CFSAN, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Chocolate and secret of Marlboro, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Chronology, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Cigarettes
    - Attributes and quitting, 1993, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Phase I & II study [summary], 1994 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Cigarettes kill [Parrish/Cippolone], undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Cippolone Harris history, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Citizens for a Sound Economy, 1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Citizens petitions
    - General, 1985-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 89 - 91)
  - Clinton, William (President), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Coalition on Smoking OR Health
    - General, 1977-1997 (Box 2, Folder 93 - 99)
    - Background & summary of petition, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Drafts of FDA letter to coalition, 1992-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Notebook [cigarettes - documentation for coalition letter], 1959-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Colby, Frank, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Columbia University School of Law
    - Class [notebook of handwritten notes], undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Remarks - Kessler, 1995, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Transcript and other notes, 1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Comparison of testimony, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Conditional approval, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Confirmation process, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Congressional
    - Letters, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Review [regulatory reform], 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Cooper, Richard, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Council for Tobacco Research (CTR)
    - General, 1978-1992 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Brown, Janet [map industry research strategy for next 25 years], 1978 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Controversy at CTR [Colorado study], 1975 (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Fight on nicotine, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Interference with CNS program will cause uproar at CTR, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - "Leads", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Legal necessity, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Notes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 120)
    - Problems at CTR, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Scientific advisory board, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Studies for legal purposes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Court of Appeals [first hearing], 1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Crawford, Victor L., 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Crohn group Washington forum, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - C-Span Live [excerpts on food, drugs, medical devices], 1992 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Dancing elephants, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Day, Lincoln H., undated (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Day One
    - General, 1968-1995, undated (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - ABC, 1993-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 131 - 132)
    - Litigation, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 133 - 134)
  - Deane, Mark v. Light, Gary D.
    - General, 1992-1997, undated (Box 3, Folder 135 - 139)
    - Attachments, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Notes, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - Vehicle [Gary Light], 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Vouchers [Light and Doyle], 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 143)
  - "Decision Memos" to Secretary Shalala re: FDA regulation of tobacco products, undated (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Democratic National Committee fax on tobacco, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Denatured alcohol, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Depository search, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Diet Pepsi, 1993-1998 (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Dietary supplements, 1991-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 149 - 151)
  - Dietrich, Paul [case study], 2000 (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - "Does a government doctor have to tell the truth" [attack on Stewart], 1967 (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - Dole, Bob, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 154)
  - Doyle, Thomas [notes], undated (Box 3, Folder 155)
  - Draft of White House statement, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Drug Abuse Advisory Committee [DAAC], 1994 (Box 4, Folder 157 - 159)
  - Du Val, Merlin K., 1994 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - E. coli, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Edgar, Hal, undated (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Edwards, Charlie [FDA cannot handle responsibilities], undated (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Electroencephalogram (EEG) [notes], 1998, undated (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Enforcement, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Enforcement hearing [statement by David Kessler], 1991 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Engle, Howard A. v. R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Co., 2000 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - European patent [process for removal of basic materials from plant products], 1988 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Ewing, Thomas W.
    - General, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 169)
    - Outside counsel, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Fan mail, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - Farone, William A.
    - General, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 172)
    - Chocolate, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 173)
    - Nitrosamines in ETS, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Federal Trade Commission (FTC), 1997 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Federal Trade Commission data, undated (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - First lawsuit, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - First meeting on cigarettes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
    - General, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 179 - 180)
    - Accelerated drug approval, 1991-1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 181 - 182)
    - Assertion of jurisdiction over cigarettes and smokeless tobacco, 1994, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 183)
    - Commissioners, undated (Box 4, Folder 184)
    - Forensic examination [cigarette photographs], undated (Box 4, Folder 185 - 189)
    - History, 1991-1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 190)
    - Position on citizens petitions, 1988, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 191)
    - Response to citizens petitions, 1988-1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 192)
    - Tobacco team, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 193)
  - Food labeling, 1991-1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - Ford, Blilely, Panetta, undated (Box 5, Folder 195)
  - Forensic Chemistry Center
    - Lab report [nicotine], 1996 (Box 5, Folder 196)
    - Photographs [groundbreaking ceremony], 1996 (Box 5, Folder 197)
  - Freedom of Information requests, 1995, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 198)
  - Fresh, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 199)
  - Full disclosure, undated (Box 5, Folder 200)
  - G7 [R. J. Reynolds], 1994, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 201)
  - Gas chromatograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - General Accounting Office
    - General, 1994-1997, undated (Box 5, Folder 203 - 207)
    - Interviews, 1994-1998 (Box 5, Folder 208 - 209)
  - Gilmore, Thomas N.
    - General, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 210)
    - Ideas and resources, 1982-1991 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Goodman, Ellen [on tobacco policy], 1999 (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - Gore, Al, 1983-2000 (Box 5, Folder 213)
  - Great American smoker project, 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 214)
  - Green, S. J. [smoking], 1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 215)
  - Handouts, undated (Box 5, Folder 216)
  - Hayden, Ronda Fae, undated (Box 5, Folder 217)
  - Heep, Hatsy, 1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Hill and Knowlton, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 219)
  - Hillary letter from Ann Witt, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 220)
  - History of industry deception, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 221)
  - Hubbard, Bill on Premiere, 1988-1997 (Box 5, Folder 222)
  - Huber, Gary L., 1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 223 - 224)
  - Human testing [R. J. Reynolds], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 225)
  - Hunter trip to Cynthiana, KY, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 226)
  - Hutt, Peter
    - General, undated (Box 6, Folder 227)
    - Excerpts on congress, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 228)
  - Ifshin, David Michael, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 229)
  - Industry
    - Memo re FDA effort to regulate tobacco as a drug, undated (Box 6, Folder 230)
    - Position, 1962-1980 (Box 6, Folder 231)
    - Research liaison committee, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 232)
  - Institute for Biological Research [INBIFO], undated (Box 6, Folder 233)
  - Institute of Medicine [study], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 234)
  - International conference on nutrition, undated (Box 6, Folder 235)
  - Investigation [Kessler summary of organizations], 1954-1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 236)
  - Javitz, Jacob to Kessler, David, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 237)
  - Jazz [non-tobacco cigarettes], 1988-1992, undated (Box 6, Folder 238)
  - Joe Camel [France], 1980, undated (Box 6, Folder 239)
  - Johnston, James W. [asserting R. J. Reynolds does not increase nicotine in their cigarettes], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 240)
  - Jurisdiction document, 1994, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 241)
  - "Keep Smiling - No One's Going to Die", 2000 (Box 6, Folder 242)
  - Kelmar, Steven B., undated (Box 6, Folder 243)
  - Kennedy, Donald, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 244)
  - Kennedy School of Government case program, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 245)
  - Kessler, David
    - FDA employee fact sheet, undated (Box 6, Folder 246)
    - Letter to William Campbell on Philip Morris visit, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 247)
    - Letters on leaving FDA, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 248)
    - Questions on DeNoble, undated (Box 6, Folder 249)
    - Spector, Sidney [retention of Kessler as commissioner], 1993 (Box 6, Folder 250)
    - Travel investigation [General Accounting Office and University of Chicago checks], 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 251 - 252)
  - Kessler and Koop on declining invitation to testify before Health & Environment Committee, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 253)
  - Kreisher, John, 1994-1995, undated (Box 6, Folder 254)
  - Kroft, Steve, 1996, undated (Box 6, Folder 255)
  - KDN extract, undated (Box 6, Folder 256)
  - Koop [tobacco company on his successor], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 257)
  - Laboratory analysis, 1994-1998 (Box 6, Folder 258 - 261)
  - Landman, Anne, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 262)
  - Leaf blenders handbook, undated (Box 6, Folder 263)
  - Lee, Brenda [ingested nicotine], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 264)
  - Legal and scientific basis for FDA's assertion of jurisdiction over cigarettes and smokeless tobacco, undated (Box 6, Folder 265)
  - Legal ethics, 1999, undated (Box 6, Folder 266)
  - Legal memos, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 267)
  - Letters [Rose-Ewing, et al.], 1994-1997 (Box 6, Folder 268 - 270)
  - Library of Congress [Kessler handwritten notes], undated (Box 6, Folder 271)
  - Liggett CEO retired, undated (Box 6, Folder 272)
  - Light, Gary and Doyle, Thomas [Kessler notes], undated (Box 6, Folder 273)
  - List given to Michael Moore, undated (Box 6, Folder 274)
  - Little, Clarence Cook, 1954-1980 (Box 7, Folder 275 - 278)
  - Long, Tim [notes], undated (Box 7, Folder 279)
  - LTR industry competitor, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 280)
  - Macon documents, 1979-1994, undated (Box 7, Folder 281 - 284)
  - Mande, Jerry, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 285)
  - Marshal, Lawrence, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 286)
  - McMahon, J. P. [young adult market], 1990 (Box 7, Folder 287)
  - Media/Congress/Clinton administration, undated (Box 7, Folder 288)
  - Media training handbook, 1991, undated (Box 7, Folder 289)
  - Meeting to discuss Ellen Cooper and Larry Kramer, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 290)
  - Merit [FDA laboratory data], 1994 (Box 7, Folder 291)
  - Merrill, Richard, 1978-1995 (Box 7, Folder 292)
  - Minnesota tobacco trial [quotes], 1998 (Box 7, Folder 293)
  - Minnesota vs. Philip Morris, undated (Box 7, Folder 294)
  - Mitchell, John R.
    - General, 1980-1997 (Box 7, Folder 295)
    - Affidavit, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 296)
    - Highlights from handbook, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 297)
    - Notes [handwritten], 1993-1998 undated (Box 7, Folder 298 - 300)
  - Mohr, Rose M., 1991 (Box 7, Folder 301)
  - More White Lights cigarettes, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 302)
  - Morris, Dick, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 303)
  - Myers, Matt
    - Notes of settlement, undated (Box 7, Folder 304)
    - Thoughts for Kessler presentation/discussions, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 305)
  - Natanblut, Sharon
    - Advertising, undated (Box 7, Folder 306)
    - Neuchasel, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 307)
    - Number of deaths, undated (Box 7, Folder 308)
    - Scenes, undated (Box 7, Folder 309)
  - National Cancer Institute [advisory board], 1992 (Box 7, Folder 310)
  - National Commission on Law Enforcement and Social Justice [whistle blowers ad], undated (Box 7, Folder 311)
  - NCTR, undated (Box 7, Folder 312)
  - Nesbit, Jeff
    - General, 1991-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 313)
    - Parrish, Steve, undated (Box 7, Folder 314)
  - Nestor, John, undated (Box 7, Folder 315)
  - Nicotine
    - Absorption through ingestion, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 316)
    - Biology, undated (Box 7, Folder 317)
    - Human fluids [RJR studies], 2000 (Box 7, Folder 318)
    - Plasma levels [what FDA was told], undated (Box 7, Folder 319)
  - Notes on public service, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 320)
  - Ochsner, Alton, 1953-1965 (Box 7, Folder 321)
  - Op-Ed piece on First Amendment, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 322)
  - Opinion/Circuit Judge Widener [FDA regulation of tobacco products], 1998 (Box 7, Folder 323)
  - Options for controlling nicotine consumption, undated (Box 7, Folder 324)
  - Oral contraceptives and smoking, undated (Box 7, Folder 325)
  - Osteen, William L., 1996 (Box 7, Folder 326)
  - "Pack of Lies" panorama, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 327)
  - Pantos, Oscar, undated (Box 7, Folder 328)
  - Patent Y-1 [letters requesting Y-1 patent application], 1994 (Box 7, Folder 329)
  - Pearson, Kim, 1998, undated (Box 7, Folder 330)
  - Pediatric statistics, undated (Box 7, Folder 331)
  - Pender, Heidi, 1994-1996, undated (Box 7, Folder 332)
  - Pertschuk, Michael [speeches], 1990-1997 (Box 7, Folder 333)
  - Philip Morris
    - Drug abuse policy, undated (Box 7, Folder 334)
    - Defamation action against ABC, undated (Box 7, Folder 335)
    - Omnibus results, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 336)
  - Phillips, Jim, 1991-1995, undated (Box 7, Folder 337)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 338 - 339)
  - Piehl, Donald H. [tar/nicotine control and smoker satisfaction], 1978 (Box 7, Folder 340)
  - Policy issues for Shalala, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 341)
  - Pollay, Richard W.
    - General, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 342)
    - Scientific smokescreen, 1954-1990 (Box 7, Folder 343)
  - Post Parrish phone call [Todd, Feiden, Kessler], undated (Box 7, Folder 344)
  - Preparation for report on smoking and health and legislative proposals, undated (Box 7, Folder 345)
  - Project Spa, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 346)
  - Public opinions about cigarette smoking, 1994, undated (Box 7, Folder 347)
  - Quotes (Box 8)
    - Showing that tobacco companies know nicotine is a drug, undated (Box 8, Folder 348)
    - Younger smokers, undated (Box 8, Folder 349)
  - R. J. Reynolds
    - Advanced technology projects [Premiere and Tom's list], undated (Box 8, Folder 350)
    - Are cigarettes drugs [John Slade], 1994 (Box 8, Folder 351)
    - Trip notes and questions, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 352 - 356)
  - Reduction of youth access and tobacco claims settlement act of 1977 [bill] (Box 8, Folder 357)
  - Regulating tobacco [outline of testimony], 1994 (Box 8, Folder 358)
  - Republican National Committee [letter to David Kessler], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 359)
  - Requests for documents from tobacco companies, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 360)
  - Research and planning, 1959-1989 (Box 8, Folder 361 - 362)
  - Research liaison committee, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 363)
  - Response to inquiries re FDA regulation of tobacco products [decision], 1993 (Box 8, Folder 364)
  - Richmond meeting, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 365)
  - Rose, Charlie
    - General, 1994-1996, undated (Box 8, Folder 366)
    - Call to Hubbard about Blilely investigations on ammonia, undated (Box 8, Folder 367)
    - Letters, 1994-1996 (Box 8, Folder 368)
  - Rothschild, Albert, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 369)
  - Russek, Henry I., 1963-1967 (Box 8, Folder 370)